We Earth system scientists
and climate scientists
are getting seriously nervous.
The planet is changing faster
than we have expected.
We are, despite years
of raising the alarm,
now seeing that the planet
is actually in a situation
where we underestimated risks.
Abrupt changes are occurring in a way
that is way beyond the realistic
expectations in science.
Fifteen years back, I introduced
the planetary boundary framework,
the scientific framework
with the nine Earth system processes
that determines the stability,
the resilience and the life support
on planet Earth.
Ten years back, the world signed
the Paris Climate Agreement.
Almost five years back,
we entered the decisive decade
where our choices
will determine the future
for all generations on planet Earth.
Where are we on this journey,
halfway into this decade?
I will give you a scientific state
of the planet report,
the most objective assessment
that science can give today.
And it starts here.
We've reached 1.2 degree Celsius
of global mean surface temperature rise,
the warmest temperature on Earth
over the past 100,000 years.
We have just scratched
on 1.5 degree Celsius
as an annual mean in 2023.
But what worries us most is this:
we are starting to see
an acceleration of warming
over the past 50 years.
0.18 degrees Celsius per decade
from 1970 to 2010.
But then from 2014 onwards,
it abruptly jumps up to 0.26 per decade.
And if we follow this path,
we will crash through two degrees
Celsius within 20 years
and hit three degrees Celsius
by the year 2100,
a disastrous outcome, caused by us humans.
But it's not only carbon dioxide.
Any parameter that matters
for human well-being and our economies
look the same.
Here you have it, linear change
up until the 1950s,
we go into the great acceleration.
And this is what we're seeing across
overconsumption of fresh water,
the sixth mass extinction of species,
over-putrefying our freshwater systems
with nitrogen and phosphorus,
all of it undermining
the stability of the planet.
As if this was not enough,
we are seeing that this is now causing
impacts across the entire economy.
We're seeing bigger and bigger invoices
being sent by the Earth system
onto societies across the entire world,
in droughts, floods,
heat waves, disease patterns,
human-reinforced storms,
scientifically attributed
to human-caused climate change.
Forty degrees Celsius
of life-threatening heat
across all continents, occurring in 2023.
Fifty-two degrees Celsius
hitting the over 1,000
who lost their lives
at the Hajj pilgrimage
in June in Mecca.
Three times higher climate change risks
now attributed to our cause
of climate change.
2023, up to 12,000 deaths,
200 billion US dollars of cost,
just in the US,
up to 100 billion US dollars.
This is seriously causing economic costs.
We have scientifically, in the past,
shown that this could cost
a few percent of global GDP
of the climate impacts caused by us.
I can tell you that the latest
scientific assessment
is what you see on the screen here.
An 18-percent loss of GDP by 2050
if we now follow the current path.
This is equivalent to 38 trillion
US dollars of loss
per year in 2050.
It's starting to hurt.
Both in human social costs
and an economic cost.
And this is happening
at 1.2 degrees Celsius
of global mean surface temperature rise.
And we're following a pathway
that takes us to 2.7 degrees Celsius
in only 70 years.
And we've had a 10,000-year period
where our civilizations have developed,
where we've had an enormous privilege
of a planet at 14 degrees Celsius,
plus or minus 0.5 degrees Celsius.
That's the Holocene
since we left the last ice age.
And if you look three million years back,
we never exceeded two degrees Celsius.
That's the warmest temperature on Earth
during the entire Quaternary.
The coldest point, minus five
degrees Celsius, Ice Age.
I call this the “corridor of life.”
Is it surprising that we scientists
are getting really, really nervous?
But it's more.
It's so much more than this.
The first issue is buffering capacity.
The second is the risk
of crossing tipping points,
and both are moving
in the wrong direction.
Buffering capacity is the Earth system's
ability to dampen shocks and stress.
Like, for example, soaking up
greenhouse gases
in intact nature on land and in the ocean.
And so far, Mother Earth
has been so forgiving.
Here we have the evidence.
What you see here is the hockey stick
of fossil fuel burning in red
and deforestation in yellow.
Is it this tremendous climate forcing
that has caused the 1.2-degree
Celsius climate crisis so far?
The answer is no.
Fifty-three percent of the carbon dioxide
from fossil fuel burning
and land system change
has been soaked up
by intact nature on land and in the ocean.
It’s only the blue sliver you see here,
which remains in the atmosphere,
causing the climate crisis so far.
The problem is
we have more and more scientific
evidence of cracks in this system.
Let's start on land.
Land absorbs 31 percent
of the carbon dioxide
from our greenhouse gas emissions.
We have more and more scientific evidence
across so much research
that the boreal forest in Canada,
or the temperate mixed forest
in Germany and Russia
are starting to lose
their carbon uptake capacity.
Did you know that the latest science shows
that the part of the Amazon rain forest,
planet Earth's richest biome
on terrestrial land,
has already tipped over
and is no longer a carbon sink?
It is today a carbon source.
It's no longer helping us.
But as if that was not enough,
what really worries us today is the ocean.
The ocean absorbs 90 percent of the heat
caused by human-induced climate change.
This is well understood,
but what really worries us
is what you see here.
This is the latest data on sea surface
temperature across the ocean.
What you see here
is from 1980 until today,
how gradually the ocean surface
just gets warmer and warmer.
It's actually warming all the way down
to 2,000 meters depth.
This is well understood in science.
It's a deep concern.
It's well represented
in the climate models,
we understand it.
Then suddenly in 2023, something happens.
Temperatures just go
completely off the charts.
0.4 degrees Celsius outside
of the warmest temperature
in previous years.
What's happening?
We admittedly must be honest here,
we do not know.
El Niño is certainly partly to blame
but cannot explain it all.
2024, it just continues.
What is happening?
We do not know.
But the candidate number one
is the energy imbalance
caused by us humans.
In one year alone,
the heat equivalent to 300 times
global electricity use
is absorbed in the Earth's system.
Is it what we see on the screen here,
an ocean that is starting
to lose resilience?
An ocean that is at risk of releasing
heat to the atmosphere
and self-amplifying warming?
We do not know.
But one thing is for certain,
the ocean is sounding the alarm.
Reasons for concern, yes.
We are now at a point
where we are forced to ask
the following question:
Are we at risk of pushing the planet
out of the basin of attraction,
the stability of the planet,
where we’ve been
since we left the last Ice Age,
the extraordinarily stable
Holocene state?
And if we pushed ourselves outside,
drifting away unstoppably
towards a hothouse Earth
where we get self-amplified warming
and losing life support on Earth.
What could take us there?
Well, we know it.
It is if we cross tipping points,
big systems like the Greenland ice sheet,
the overturning of heat
in the North Atlantic,
the coral reef systems,
the Amazon rainforest
are tipping element systems.
Push them too far, and they will flip over
from a desired state that helps us
to a state that will self-amplify
in the wrong direction,
going from cooling and dampening
to self-amplifying and warming.
A rainforest tips over
to a Savannah state.
Now we have now mapped
the 16 tipping element systems,
which are now scientifically cataloged,
that regulate the climate system.
These 16, and you see the five
in the ground zero on planet Earth,
in the Arctic,
are connected via cascades
through the ocean,
particularly via the AMOC,
the Atlantic overturning
of heat in the ocean,
all the way down to Antarctica.
These are big biophysical systems
that we all depend on,
global commons for
the stability of the planet.
The question is, at what temperatures
are they at risk of tipping
from helping us to becoming
self-amplifying foes?
Well, for the first time,
we have an attempt
to answer that question.
What you see here are the 16 tipping
element systems on the y axis,
and in red you see the uncertainty range,
the best estimates in science,
darker the red,
the higher the risk of tipping,
it's the temperature levels
at which they're likely
to cross the threshold.
The average temperature
at which they are likely to tip
is the yellow circle lines you see here.
What this tells us is the following.
Five of these 16 are likely
to cross the tipping points
already at 1.5 degrees Celsius.
The Greenland ice sheet,
the West Antarctic ice sheet,
abrupt thawing of permafrost,
losing all tropical coral reef systems
and collapse of the Barents Sea ice.
And just the two ice sheets
hold ten-meter sea level rise,
which would be unstoppable
on the long term.
Now sure, there is scientific
uncertainty here,
as you see from these graphs,
but there's one red thread in science
for humanity in the scientific message.
And it's this: the more we understand
of the Earth's system,
the higher is the risk.
And here is the proof.
This is five IPCC assessments
the Intergovernmental Panel
on Climate Change,
30 years of scientific advancements.
Here again you see risk assessment,
darker the red, higher the likelihood
of causing irreversible change
in the climate system.
Thirty years back, the risk
was put at five degrees Celsius
of tipping
and coming down
to current state of science,
the risk is set at 1.5
to two degrees Celsius.
We are in the midst
of a danger zone today.
But it can be even worse than that.
Let's go to the Amazon basin, again,
the richest terrestrial ecosystem on land,
climate science estimates the risk
of the Amazon rainforest
tipping over irreversibly to a savanna
at three to five degrees
of global mean surface temperature rise.
A really high temperature,
unlikely even to be met
over the next 70 years.
But if we lose forest cover,
the risk is that the system can
tip already at 1.5 to two degrees Celsius
if we lose more than 20
to 25 percent of forest cover.
So that's a very dangerous combination.
Where are we today?
We are at 1.2 degrees Celsius of global
mean surface temperature rise
and 17 percent of deforestation.
We are very close to a tipping point
in the Amazon rainforest.
Very close.
What shall we do to avoid
these unmanageable outcomes?
Well, the IPCC is clear on the pathway.
To stay under 1.5 degrees Celsius,
to avoid crossing tipping points,
we need to operate, to navigate
within the global carbon budget
that gives us a chance of holding 1.5.
What remains for us is only 200 billion
tons of carbon dioxide
that we can continue emitting
to have a 50 percent chance
of holding 1.5.
We emit today 40 billion tons
of carbon dioxide per year,
giving us five years
at current rates of emission
before we've consumed the budget.
We are seriously running out of time.
And the pathway for a safe landing
is also well studied and understood.
You have it here.
Bend the curve of emissions immediately
and follow a path
where we reduce emissions
by at least seven percent per year
for a safe landing
and a net zero world economy by 2050.
But it's more than that.
We also know that even
if we succeed with this,
we have already loaded the atmosphere
with so much greenhouse gases,
with so much climate forcing,
that we inevitably face
a period of overshoot.
We must now be prepared
for a very likely breaching
of the 1.5-degree-Celsius
planetary boundary on climate
somewhere between 2030 and 2035.
In five to 10 year's time.
And then have, at best,
a 30-40 year period of overshoot
before we can come back
to 1.5 by the end of this century.
We would exceed
with 0.1 to 0.3 degrees Celsius
the 1.5 limit,
meaning up to 1.8 degrees Celsius.
What does this tell us?
Well, I can tell you there are
two main messages.
Message one:
Buckle up.
We know for certain,
100 percent certainty,
that this means
more droughts, more floods,
more heat waves,
more human-reinforced storms,
more disease during one generation's time.
2023, the warmest year on record,
will be looked back upon as a mild year.
Message two.
Why would the planet come back
to 1.5 after overshoot?
Well, the answer is very simple.
The health of the planet
must be kept intact.
We must continue having a planet
that can absorb 50 percent
of the carbon dioxide.
We must have a planet
that crosses no tipping points.
We must have a planet that remains healthy
and keeping heat intact in the ocean.
That is why we need planetary boundaries.
The planetary boundary framework
that defines the nine
Earth system processes
that regulates the stability
and resilience of the entire planet:
climate, biodiversity, nitrogen,
phosphorus, land, fresh water,
air pollutants and chemicals.
That is the challenge.
To summarize that,
there is no 1.5 degrees Celsius delivery
on the Paris Agreement
by only phasing out fossil fuels.
We also need to come back
into the safe operating space
of the nature-based biodiversity,
all the planetary boundaries of nature.
This means that science is clear.
The window is rapidly closing,
but there is still
some light in the window.
We actually have evidence
that we've reached a pivotal point,
not only in terms of risk,
but also in terms of opportunity
to transform the world
towards a safe and just
future for humanity.
Linear change is no longer an option.
The only option is exponential change.
We know that the only currency
that matters is speed and scale.
We also need to become stewards
of the entire planet.
We need to now recognize,
from local to global level,
that we're all so intertwined
that we must govern the entire planet.
I know,  that is very daunting,
but what choice do we have
when on the line is the future
of our children
on planet Earth?
And we have the solutions.
We know that solving
the planet crisis is not utopia.
It's not fantasy.
We have the solutions for a secure,
stable future for humanity.
What are those transformations?
Well, we know them.
It's a rapid transition
away from fossil fuels.
It is a transition towards
circular business models.
It is transitioning towards healthy diets
from sustainable food systems.
And it's not only halting loss of nature,
it's also scaling the regeneration
and restoration of marine systems, soils,
forests and wetlands.
We have solutions for all of these.
Just take green energy,
which today is cheaper
than fossil fuel-based energy.
It's our choice that we're facing today.
Now I was nervous already in 2020
when we entered this decisive decade
and had to cut global emissions
by half by 2030.
Halfway into this decade,
the road is steeper than ever.
It's steeper than ever.
This is what really, really concerns us.
That we have a situation
where we now need to move so fast.
And I've been standing on stages
like this so many times,
sharing the dire scientific diagnostic.
But still, I just told you
that I do conclude that there is
still some window open.
There is a light in the tunnel.
And you may ask, what is it
that makes me able to continue
to be a realistic optimist
in this situation?
The most dire situation, I must admit,
in my whole professional life.
Well, actually, I promise
this is an honest statement.
there are so many positive items as well.
The most important one in my mind
is that we have ample evidence
that citizens across the world,
a majority of them,
care about nature and climate.
They trust climate science,
they're concerned about climate change,
and they want solutions.
And the second key factor
is that we have so much evidence today
that the solutions are not only available,
but if we implement them,
we get a more healthy, stable,
secure future with the jobs
and the economies
that can compete and provide
livelihoods into the future.
This means, dear friends,
that solving the planetary crisis
is not only necessary,
it is possible,
and we all win if we succeed.
Thank you very much.
(Applause)